Guide to the William Henry Chafe Oral History Collection, 1933-1988 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Henry Chafe Oral History collection 1933-1988 and undated
Chafe, William Henry
5.6 linear feet Extent: circa 2930 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00222
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The William Henry Chafe Oral History Collection has been restricted due to the absence of release forms transferring intellectual property rights from interviewees or interviewers to researchers using this collection. Researchers are cautioned that the publication of information contained in these interviews may violate the legal rights of interviewees or interviewers. It is the sole responsibility of researchers to secure permission from interviewees or interviewers to publish quotes from either, and to ensure that information gained from research in this collection is not used in any way that violates rights remaining with interviewees, interviewers or their heirs.
Patrons who wish to use this collection must sign a restricted materials research agreement, which may be obtained from any Special Collections reference staff person.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Henry Chafe Oral History Collection was donated to Special Collections in 1987 and 2011 by William Henry Chafe.
Collection Overview
The William Henry Chafe Oral History Collection spans the years 1933 through 1988, with most of the materials dated between 1972 and 1978. The collection consists mainly of oral history interview tapes and transcripts, but also includes interview notes and research files related to Chafe's book Civilities and Civil Rights: Greensboro, North Carolina, and the Black Struggle for Freedom.
The interview tapes and transcripts (1972-1978, undated), which comprise the bulk of the collection, include interviews with government officials, participants in the North Carolina civil rights movement of the 1950s and 1960s, and opponents of the movement, including members of the Ku Klux Klan. The few research files in the collection include statistical data related to Greensboro elections (1930s-1950s), notes from the Joan Bluethenthal papers and a report by the North Carolina State Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights on civil disturbances at Dudley High School and North Carolina A&T State University in Greensboro, North Carolina in 1969.
The Audiotapes Series consists of two identical sets (one for preservation, one for use by researchers) of twenty-eight tapes containing oral history interviews. The Printed Material Series includes transcripts and/or notes on 67 oral history interviews, and three research files related to the civil rights movement and local politics in Greensboro.
Beyond the direct oral history materials, there is also a Writings and Research Series. It includes research notes for several chapters of Chafe's book in addition to newspaper clippings addressing topics such as Martin Luther King, Jr.'s assassination and the return of black veterans from the Vietnam War; an assortment of documents regarding the Black Panther Party collected by the Federal Bureau of Investigations' Counter Intelligence Program, and a number of publications produced by other authors. While the materials predominately relate to Greensboro, this series also includes information on civil rights activity in Durham, Chapel Hill, and the Research Triangle at large. The Photographs Series includes fourteen undated photographs.
William H. Chafe's book, Civilities and Civil Rights: Greensboro, North Carolina, and the Black Struggle for Freedom, chronicles the continuing conflict over desegregation in Greensboro in the 1950s and 1960s. Chafe explores the "progressive mystique" that defined the terms of culturally-sanctioned behavior, looking at how civility served to preserve the South's racial order. Within this context, he discusses the city's reaction to the Supreme Court's landmark decision in Brown v. Board of Education in 1954, the Greensboro sit-in movement begun by four college students at North Carolina A&T College in 1960, and the emergence of the Black Power Movement in the late 1960s.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Martin Luther King, Jr. and the Civil Rights Movement.; Afro-Americans -- Civil rights -- North Carolina.; Afro-Americans -- North Carolina -- Greensboro -- Social conditions.; North Carolina A&T State University.; United States Commission on Civil Rights.; Black Panther Party.; Black power -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Civil rights -- North Carolina -- Greensboro.; Ku Klux Klan (1915- )--North Carolina -- Greensboro.; Greensboro (N.C.)--Race relations.; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1951-
Related Material
Behind the Veil: Documenting African-American Life in the Jim Crow South. 1940-1997 and undated (bulk 1993-1997),
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Audiotapes Series, 1972-1978 and undated
  This series includes two identical sets of taped oral history interviews (1972-1978 & undated) related to the civil rights movement in Greensboro, North Carolina. The master tapes in subseries A serve as preservation copies and are closed to researchers; subseries B contains a complete set of use copies, which are open for use by all patrons.
  - Subseries A, Master Tapes
    - Allen, Carolyn (Box 1)
    - Bailey, Tom
    - Bishop, Cecil
    - Brandon, Lewis
    - Breathett, George/Troxler, Kay
    - Chavis, Vance
    - Elam, Jack
    - English, Ike/Notes on C of C docs.
    - Ford, Robert
    - Foster, John (2 tapes)
    - Hariston, Otis
    - Hudgkins, R. E./Brown, W. R. (KKK)
    - Jackson, William
    - Johnson, Walter/Johnson, Nelson
    - Jones, Mrs. David
    - Knox, Joe
    - McNeill, Joseph
    - Parker, Mrs. Franklin
    - Player, Willa
    - Price, Jim
    - Sanford, Terry/Johnson, Nelson
    - Schenck, David
    - Smith, Louise
    - Taylor, John and Betsy
    - Troxler, Evelyn
    - Weaver, Mike
    - Zane, Edward R.
  - Subseries B, Use Tapes
    - Allen, Carolyn (Box 2)
    - Bailey, Tom
    - Bishop, Cecil
    - Brandon, Lewis
    - Breathett, George/Troxler, Kay
    - Chavis, Vance
    - Elam, Jack
    - English, Ike/Notes on C of C docs.
    - Ford, Robert
    - Foster, John (2 tapes)
    - Hariston, Otis
    - Hudgkins, R. E./Brown, W. R. (KKK)
    - Jackson, William
    - Johnson, Walter/Johnson, Nelson
    - Jones, Mrs. David
    - Knox, Joe
    - McNeill, Joseph
    - Parker, Mrs. Franklin
    - Player, Willa
    - Price, Jim
    - Sanford, Terry/Johnson, Nelson
    - Schenck, David
    - Smith, Louise
    - Taylor, John and Betsy
    - Troxler, Evelyn
    - Weaver, Mike
    - Zane, Edward R.
- Printed Materials Series, 1933-1978(bulk 1972-1978)
  This series consists primarily of transcripts (subseries A) and notes on 67 interviews (1972-1978, undated) about the civil rights movement in Greensboro.
  This series also includes three files of research materials (subseries B), including data on the Greensboro elections, 1930s -1950s; notes on the papers of Joan Bluethenthal; and a report by the North Carolina State Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights on civil disturbances at Dudley High School and North Carolina A&T State University in Greensboro, North Carolina in 1969.
  - Transcripts
    - Ashby, Warren, 1974, Oct. 3 (Box 2)
    - Bailey, Tom, 1977, July 9
    - Bardolph, Richard, 1972, July 11
    - Bell, Tart, 1977, Oct. 13
    - Bishop, Cecil, 1977, summer
    - Blackwell, Randolph, 1973, Mar. 5, undated (2 folders)
    - Blair, Mr. and Mrs. Ezell, 1972, Mar. 13
    - Bluethenthal, Joan, 1977, July 13
    - Bowles, Mrs. Charles, 1974, Sept. 24
    - Brandon, Lewis, undated
    - Breathett, George, undated
    - Brown, Sarah Mendenhall, 1974, July 14
    - Brown, Walter R. "Dub" and Hudgins, Robert by Scott Ellsworth
    - Chavis, Vance, 1973, May 20
    - Coley, Nell, 1974, Oct. 15
    - Dawson, Eddie (KKK) by Scott Ellsworth, 1977, May 26
    - Davis, Charles, undated
    - Dowdy, Lewis, 1975, Jan. 21
    - Edmonds, Rev. Ed, undated
    - Elam, Jack, undated
    - Evans, Dr. George, undated
    - Ezell, Blair (now Jibreel Khazan), 1974, Nov. 27
    - Falkeners, Waldo, 1972, July 19
    - Flora, Joe, 1974, Sept. 26
    - Ford, Bob, 1977, June 17
    - Ford, S. N. (interview and FBI information), undated
    - Foster, John, 1973, Feb. 9
    - Gardner, Plato by Scott Ellsworth, 1977, May 26
    - Hairston, Otis, 1972, July 17; 1977 (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - House, W. A., undated
    - Hudgins, D. E., 1972, July 6
    - Hudgins, Eula, 1974, Dec. 17
    - Jackson, William, 1977, July 12
    - Jarrett, Hobart, undated
    - Johnson, Nelson, 1978, Oct. 24
    - Jones, Mrs. David, undated
    - Knox, Joe, 1977, June 17
    - Lewis, John by Jack Bass, undated
    - Linck, R. B., 1974, Oct. 10
    - Lineberry, Al, 1974, Dec. 17
    - Mark, Carolyn, 1974, Oct. 10
    - McCoy, Cleo, 1977, Sept. 6
    - McNeill, Joseph, 1978
    - Morehead, David, 1974, Dec. 19
    - Parker, Willa, 1977, Dec. 2
    - Price, Jim by Scott Ellsworth, 1977, May 25
    - Richmond, David by Clay Carson, 1972, Apr. 10
    - Roach, George, 1972, July 17
    - Sanford, Terry, undated
    - Sieber, Hal, undated
    - Simkins, Anna, undated
    - Simpkins, Dr. & Mrs. George, 1972, July 19
    - Smith, Ben, 1973, June 6
    - Smith, Louise, 1973, Feb. 9
    - Smith, McNeill, 1973, July 14
    - Smith, Raymond, 1973, July 11
    - Snider, William, 1974, Dec. 19
    - Snider, William, 1976, Nov. 9
    - Stephenson Kiliminjaro, John Marshall, 1972, Nov. 2
    - Stoneburner, Carol, 1974, Dec. 12
    - Taylor, John & Betsy, 1973, July 7
    - Thomas, William, undated
    - Troxler, Kay, 1973, June 6
    - Weaver, Mike, 1977, July 6
    - Zane, Edward R, undated
  - Research Files
    - Bluethenthal, Joan (Box 2)
    - Political materials
    - Trouble in Greensboro, 1969 Civil Rights Demos.
- Writings and Research Series, 1956-1988 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Roughly one-half of this series consists of Chafe's notes for Civilities and Civil Rights: Greensboro, North Carolina, and the Black Struggle for Freedom. Notes are divided by chapter. Also included in this series are photocopies of the Federal Bureau of Investigation's Counter Intelligence Program documents pertaining to Black Panther Party members and chapters in Charlotte, N.C. and Oakland, C.A. Series includes reports and writings by others related to Chafe's book, a number of newspaper clippings, two interview transcripts of Ella Baker conducted by Sue Thrasher and Casey Hayden, and information on Civil Rights protests in Durham, Chapel Hill, Greensboro, and the campuses of North Carolina Central University and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
  - Chapter 2 notes, (6 folders) (Box 3)
  - Chapter 3 notes, (8 folders)
  - Chapter 4 notes, (2 folders)
  - Chapter 5 notes, (3 folders)
  - Chapter 7 notes
  - Chapter 8 notes, (4 folders)
  - Black Panther Party COINTELPRO documents, (4 folders)
  - COINTELPRO Report on Counterorientation Week at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1969
  - North Carolina Central University activism, 1958-1960
  - Chapel Hill Civil Rights Movement oral history interviews, 1974
  - Research Triangle Civil Right chronolgical list, undated
  - Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.'s speech at White Rock Baptist Church, Durham, 1960 Feb. 16
  - Newspaper clippings on the assassination of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., 1968-1977
  - Newspaper clippings, 1970-1973
  - Mayor's Committee on Human Relations, Durham, 1960
  - Greensboro Mens Club: Four Decades, 1970
  - The People of Guilford: Growth and Changes in the Population of Guilford County, 1972
  - The Role of the Department of Health, Education and Welfare in the Desegregation of the Greensboro, N.C. School System, Julie Buttenwieser, 1988
  - School Desegregation in Greensboro, 1954-1971, 1971
  - So Much History, So Much Future: Martin Luther King, Jr. and the Second Coming of America, Vincent Harding, 1979
  - The Solicitor General's Office, Justice Frankfurter and Civil Rights Litigation, 1946-1960: An Oral History, Philip Elman, 1987
  - Urbanization, Employment, and Race Relations in Greensboro, North Carolina, 1870-1910, Samuel M. Kipp, III, undated
  - Ella Baker interview transcripts and notes, 1974 and undated
  - Adele Clark oral history transcript, 1964 Feb. 28
  - Notes on the Edward R. Zane Papers, undated
  - Notes on the Greensboro Community Fellowship Papers, undated
  - Simkins v. Cone Hospital United States District Court decision, 1962
  - Oral history notes, undated
  - Correspondence, 1974-1978
  - Oral History Project Status Updates, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Chapel Hill Oral History Conference, 1974 and Undated (2 Folders)
  - Papers Written by Chapel Hill Conferees, 1974
  - JD Tarpley Biography, 1977
  - Frank McCain Questions, undated
  - Foster Materials-Desegregation, 1957-1958
  - Governor Luther Hodges Papers, 1955 and Undated
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1954-1957
  - Southern Regional Council: Emory Via's Field Trip to Greensboro, undated
  - Daily News Coverage of King Death, 1968 April 1
  - Ku Klux Klan News Articles 1974, 1977
  - Ku Klux Klan Meetings 1957-58, 1958-1977
  - Documents for William Chafe, 1978-1980
  - Chapter 1 notes: Black Community 1930-1954, undated
  - Chapter 1 notes: Kipp and Early History, undated
  - Benjamin Muse Memo in Sit-Ins, 1960 March 8
  - School Desegregation Clippings: 1963-1970, 1957-1964
  - Oral History Papers, 1973
  - Research Notes on Greensboro, 1959-1978 and Undated
  - Greensboro Community Fellowship, 1959-1980, (12 folders)
  - American Friends Service Committee Archive Notes: Southeast Region, 1977 September 9
  - Kornegay Papers, 1963-1979
  - American Friends Service Committee Papers, undated
  - Sanford Papers, undated
  - Sociological Articles on Race, 1963-1978 and undated
  - American Friends Service Committee Xeroxes, 1956-1960 and undated
  - American Friends Service Committee Papers: Philadelphia, 1953-1958
  - Hal Sieber Letters and Clippings, 1970-1973
  - Moore Papers, undated
  - Press Clippings, 1959-1963
  - Press Clippings, 1959-1963
  - Miscellaneous, 1960-1964
  - Press Clippings, 1962-1963, (2 folders)
  - Governor Robert Scott Papers, undated
  - School Board Minutes, 1960
  - M.A. Thesis on Sit-Ins, undated (Box 5)
  - Summary Notes for 1973 Greensboro Paper at OAH: Books, Census, Paper, 1956-1973
  - Notes for SHA Sit-In Paper, undated
  - Early Draft of Sit-In with Goodwyn Comments, undated
  - Gerda Lerner Papers, 1987
  - Untitled, 1987, (4 folders)
  - Inventory of Files, undated
  - Chapter 3, undated
  - Chapter 4: The Continuing Struggle, undated, (3 folders)
  - Chapter 5, undated
  - Draft of Chapter 6, undated
  - Epilogue, undated
  - Pearsall Plan Thesis, 1977 and undated
  - Paper on Sit-Ins as Delivered, undated
  - Bill Lucas Paper on School Desegregation, undated
  - Kipp Dissertation Xeroxes, undated
  - Kipp Dissertation Notes, 1974
  - Marian Stroble "Pearsall Plan," 1973
  - Tom Noland "Brown Decision," 1972
  - Leuchtenburg Comment on Sit-In Article, 1977
  - Comments on 1974 Organization of American Historians Paper, 1973
  - Greensboro Names, 1971 and undated
  - Greensboro Bibliography, 1960-1966 and undated
  - Summary Notes on Early Interviews: Names, undated
  - Greensboro National Endowment for the Humanities Application, 1974
  - Chapter 1, undated, (2 folders)
  - Untitled, 1987 and undated
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Application, undated
  - John Thorner Paper on Press Coverage of Sit-Ins, 1972
  - Bernadine Moses Thesis on Carolina Peacemaker, undated
  - Organization of American Historians Greensboro Paper,1973
  - ID Newby Black Carolinians, 1973
  - Untitled, 1987
  - References, 1985-1987 (Box 6)
  - Chafe Letters, 1987
  - Dolores Sullivan, 1987
  - Tax Returns, 1980
  - Itineraries, 1980-1986
  - ICA and European Trip, 1982-1984
  - University Publications of America, 1986
  - Oral History Book Manuscript, 1977
  - Kennedy Library Material, undated
  - Women in Higher Education, 1978
  - Asheville Speech: Family, 1977
  - Newspaper Clips, 1975-1976 and Undated
  - Tom Norton "Worker Dissent," undated
  - Ronnie Dugger, undated
  - Daniel Levine: Conservatism and Tradition in Danish Social Welfare Legislation, undated
  - Student Papers, 1971-1973
  - Violence in Family Material, undated
  - Carolina Peacemaker, undated
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1973-1977 and undated
  - Notes for Chapter 8, 1963-1977 and undated, (3 folders)
  - Benjamin L Smith Papers, 1956 and undated
- Photographs Series, undated, (1 box)
  Series consists of 14 photographs located in the final folder of box 3. Photographs show Civil Rights demonstrators, law enforcement response, race relations in the South, and active protest. All photographs are undated with little information regarding subjects and locations, though three photographs are identifiably of Chapel Hill demonstrations.
  - Photographs (Box 3)